AI is moving insanely fast. You've said
that compared to AI that humans are
going to see their value go negative.
What do you mean by that?
>> Yeah, I think it's I said precisely the
value of human cognition, we've got
about two years before it goes negative.
We're the dumbest people on the team.
You know, we're slowing everyone else
down. In fact, I remember we had our
first podcast 3 years ago
>> and I said it was going to be three
years until everything changes and now
this is the point of change. Now, do you
think that we've actually hit that point
of change to make good on that
statement?
>> I'm a mathematician. Navia Stokes
problem was solved. You know, like
you've just seen another genetic
breakthrough. You've seen competent AI
that doesn't make mistakes. Hollywood
level video. I think now is the takeoff
point. And again, we've got one or two
years before our AI teammates look at us
with disgust and be like, man, that
emad, you know, always say the dumbest
things. The first three years were
basically getting up to the point where
it could have the Navier Stokes type
breakthrough.
>> Yeah.
>> Now it's going to be where we're racing
over the next couple of years where
we're right now we're able to use it.
We're able to be meaningful in the mix,
but that is going to be a declining arc
that somewhere in the neighborhood of
two years it's we're the guy that
they're basically paying to leave the
team.
>> Yeah. Like we're the team is more
efficient without you. like the
technology and the models have got to
that human level performance. They're
about to outstrip us. But the hard
>> say they're about to outstrip us. What
what is it?
>> If you look at the outputs, you have an
AI slot for the longest time. Like you
can tell AI writing for example, you
know, like it's like you're half right,
half wrong, and the part that's half
wrong is the interesting one. You know,
it's not X but Y.
>> Yeah. God, there we go. You know, like
you're picking up the slot. That's all
disappearing with the next generation of
models.
>> The next generation of models don't make
mistakes. Like as a mathematician
studying maths at Oxford, I was better
than the AI at generalized understanding
of math until maybe a few months ago and
then it stripped ahead and now it's
solving the hardest math problems in the
world.
>> In terms of just everyday stuff, end of
last year, we had the open claw
phenomenon, right? Everyone's like, "Oh,
look at this and let's buy some Mac
minis and things like that." And then
they realized it's actually kind of
garbage. It makes lots of mistakes, you
know, it likes deleted all my stuff.
>> And the open claw moment was a gentic
AI. It will go do things on my behalf.
>> It go do things on your behalf. Now what
we have is Muse and Instinct and things
like that. Actually,
>> people that don't know them,
>> it's like actual AI agents that you just
message and they go and book you
restaurants at the coolest tables or
they like check your kids school
activities. They're like a really good
PA,
>> you know, but they actually are good.
They don't drop the ball. So, you've
gone from AI dropping the ball,
hallucinating, writing like crap to all
of a sudden it's good. Actually, it's
competent. And the next level is when
you get 10,000 of them together like
OpenAI did, solving this incredibly
difficult math problem,
>> Navier Stokes.
>> Navia Stokes. Yeah. So, there were seven
millennium prize problems, a million
dollars each. Humans solved one, it
solved the second one. Did it actually
solve Navier Stokes or just progress it?
>> So, the prizes have certain conditions
and Navia Stokes had four different
conditions that could win it. Um, they
solved two of them. The other two are
still to be solved, but a solution of
those two counts as everything, but it's
not the whole like Navia Stokes problems
that we have. It's a specific set of
things. So, they won the prize. You
know, there's still more to solve in
math. But the question sure because I
don't I think it's currently listed as
active meaning we're assessing. We
haven't fully decided yet. And there was
obviously the big debate between was it
the humans that did this or was it open
AI?
>> Yeah. So this is a problem that I've
looked at and actually studied formally
and things like that. Um it takes two
years
to actually accept it.
>> Whoa. That's the Clay Institute thing.
So it needs to be published in a journal
then needs to be accepted and two years
need to go by with people beating it up.
What OpenAI did is they put 10,000
agents for 88 hours on it, which is a
hundred years of talented human time
>> and then they had a formal proof. So
like you can click a button and then it
just checks it formally and says right
or wrong. So it's highly unlikely to be
wrong. Like humans can't do that because
it's so freaking exhaustive. Like
there's a theorem called Fermat's last
theorem. The official proof of that is
127 pages. anthropic
>> formalize that proof. It's 13 million
lines of code.
>> Oh my god.
>> So that's another thing again for us
mathematicians this is a bit existential
because we're like what do we even do
now? Like some of my buddies who are
doing math PhDs are like these formal
proofs are coming out like I don't even
know what to study next. In fact, OpenAI
a couple of days ago said we have solved
a hundred of the top mathematics
problems but we're holding them back for
now because we don't want to make the
mathematician sad. Like okay fair
enough. That seems very strange. But
before we get to that, I want to push on
the Navy or Stokes things for a second.
So that really it's a delineating line
for you in a way that I don't think a
lot of people understand.
>> I think, and correct me if I'm wrong,
that this comes down to what I think of
as the Yan Lun thing. So Yan Lun is like
LLMs just aren't the architecture that's
going to work. It's always going to be
merely a vomit back of patterns that we
see humans do. We're limited by what
humans have figured out. So is it that
you think Navy or Stokes was novel, was
not something in the training data, and
therefore it expressly proves that
theory wrong and we're seeing now that
it can think beyond its training data?
Yes, as of the last month and a half,
the models have gone beyond their
training data definitively. So before
Navia Stokes, um, OpenAI released 10
proofs of famous math problems. And I
can say at least two of them. Con's
conjecture being the main one is
definitively novel, elegant, and never
seen before. The way they did that
proof.
>> Navia Stokes, it did it in a bit of a
more mechanical way, but again in an
incredibly novel way. It's quite
difficult to read because it's like AI
slop claudism when you're reading it. So
it took like me, it took 3 days for me
to even read the paper, you know, and I
haven't gone through the formal stuff.
But I've talked to enough of my
mathematician buddies now because we
obviously we discussed this to say yeah
human could have done this given 20 30
years. So the first millennium price
problem the punky conjecture was solved
by gregori pearlman.
>> Have you heard about this story?
>> No.
>> Gregori pearlman was a very famous
mathematician and he just dropped off
the grid
>> for like 10 20 years.
>> Yeah.
>> Then he emerges on arriv. He dropped the
proof of ponury conjecture. Everyone
thought it was a topology problem. It
turned out to be a partial differential
equation problem and it's like again 130
pages of proofs and then they were like
we're going to give you a million
dollars. This is fantastic. Come on our
thing. It's like no like why the proof
being right is enough. Don't contact me
again. And then he drops off the grid
again.
>> That's so wild.
>> Which is the boss move, right? Like
that's what you do.
>> And so this one here again, it reminds
you of Pearlman in the way that it's
done and it's clearly like way beyond
average PhD level. And the fact that
they could scale it by attacking it with
a 10,000 means that these types of math
problems are formally verifiable and you
can just literally chuck compute at
them. So is it that it's going beyond
the human ability it's reaching beyond
its training data or is it that it's
learned from humans and then it can just
throw a 100red years of compute at it
over a weekend?
>> I think it's both now. Um starting
August 29th, OpenAI had a new type of
model training. So they had an existing
model that they figured out a trick with
that made it go from 10% on Frontier
Math a benchmark to 60% overnight
>> and just started solving these math
problems one after the other. It's like
if you use the new Opus all of a sudden
it can do amazing 3D scenes and
photorealistic water and like generate
entire songs or Astra is the same like
it suddenly got eyes. it suddenly had a
sense of positioning and taste. So we've
kind of reached this point where these
models have suddenly gained another
capability which the capability to
conceptualize
and so there's something internal going
on within them. We've seen this in
previously in the video models where the
video models had terrible physics like
when we first came out with the first
video models we were like do gymnastics
you remember that hilarious yeah spines
would just spin.
>> Yeah. or Will Smith eating spaghetti.
Now they do it flawlessly
and they've learned physics. So you can
say like, I want a boat made of sugar
cubes and a boat made of concrete and a
boat made of wood and it will actually
accurately show them dropping into the
water
>> as in the sugar cube will melt or
>> the sugar cube will kind of float and
then it will melt.
>> Huh.
>> Like again, it's learning these things.
It's learning representations. And
something has happened in the last few
months that has allowed the math
breakthroughs that has allowed the
gaming breakthroughs again. Like a year
ago, all the websites that Claude made
looked like the same like the weird
purple. Do you remember that?
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Now it can do like crazy 3JS dynamic
websites that pop out and dance and
stuff like that, right? Um, and so this
is a tipping point and again like I
don't think anything in math is safe.
It's one of the most formally verifiable
ones but even outside of that we're
seeing human level performance drop. In
fact two days ago uh the AI is tied the
best humans in super forecasting.
>> I don't know what super forecasting is.
>> So there are some humans who are better
than others at forecasting things
>> like what? um like outcomes of political
campaigns, who's going to win elections
and things like you remember Nate Silver
back in the good old days and 538.
>> I've heard of but don't
>> there's a competition. It's met
Metalculus is the website that kind of
tracks these things and so every year
they have this super forecasting
championship where the best human teams
come together and forecast stuff. AI has
just tied the best human
>> and obviously it will beat the best
human now and that's something that's
open-ended because math is kind of
deterministic like you think a computer
should be able to do math better than a
human really like this highle conceptual
math is a bit different but it's got
there and now it's got there in
open-ended domains and it's got their
own in design and now it's getting taste
which we never thought the AI would get
and it's not writing like slop.
Okay. So, three years ago, you make a
prediction. It comes true. I mean,
within a couple of months, were you gut
feeling your way through that or were
you doing something based on I know the
rate at which chips get faster or better
and therefore it's going to be roughly 3
years?
>> Pretty much that it's a straight line
extrapolation.
>> Okay. So, where does your straight line
extrapolation take you now? just it's
better than humans at virtually
everything in 2 years.
>> Uh yes, and it's integrated and it's
accessible. So you can push a button and
replace your entire workforce with
digital twins of them that have the same
bad humor and everything and you can't
tell it.
>> Meaning you can train the AI on a
specific human.
>> Yes. So it will look through all of the
Zoom calls, all of the discussions, all
of the word documents and replicate that
human. So you can Zoom call them. Like
you're going to see in the next couple
of months. Um I don't know and they
might be out already actually. A whole
bunch of companies have built frontends
for your agents that you can zoom call
and WhatsApp and normal call and it just
looks like a person. It's live video
now. All the mannerisms, everything.
It'll replicate them exactly. Replicate
the voice. Exactly. Replicate the humor
exactly.
slightly creepy, but you know, again,
>> slightly creepy because it's uncanny
valley or slightly creepy because of the
implications.
>> It's not uncalien valley. That's what's
creepy about it
>> because you worry about as we stretch
into the future, there's literally no
distinguishing characteristic between an
actual human and an AI.
>> Yeah, you don't know. On the other side
of the screen now, as of the latest
video models, you don't know. As of the
latest voice models, you don't know.
again everything has gone that uncanny
valley that we had
that's been overcome.
>> Now are there models that you've seen
that make you say that because I
interface with these models in a
production environment where I'm trying
to implement things into the game or I'm
trying to write music which I was just
doing yesterday for the game. You can
still feel the AI quality. It's amazing
but it's still there. So I s I will say
even if nobody else thinks you're a
little bit crazy, I think you're a
little bit crazy cuz I I can still feel
the AIness, but I'm dealing with
commercial overthe-c counter models. Are
you saying this based on the commercial
overthe-counter models and your
standards are just lower than mine or
you see something I don't see?
>> No, I see all I see a lot of models that
are released.
>> So there's something that hasn't quite
hit the market yet that makes you that
confident.
>> Some of the models have hit the market,
some of the models haven't. So the math
models have not hit the market. We do
not have access to these models that can
solve a hundred of the top math
equations.
>> We have harnessed
>> and sorry who was it you were saying is
keeping that because they don't want to
make so open AI has solved more math but
they don't want to upset mathematicians.
>> Yeah. So they've created this math
board. There was a whole outcry by
mathematicians like sounds like you know
when we released stable diffusion all
the artists like you're taking away our
jobs and things like that. This is not
what math is for. Math is about the
struggle
>> you know.
>> Well I mean again think about it. You're
a PhD in math. You're doing a pure math
PhD thinking for years and then the AI
comes and solves it for a buck 50.
>> Yeah, sort of. We'll be right back to
the show. First though, let's talk about
how creators are paying people to do
work that software now does in just a
few clicks. Our team uses Opus Clip. You
drop in a long video, it finds the
strongest moments and cuts them into
shorts. That [music] part is awesome,
but it's also the least impressive thing
that Opus does. Opus clip refframes your
footage for vertical videos so faces and
whatever matters stay in [music] the
frame. It upscales the video so the
finished clip looks sharper than what
you shot. It generates B-roll based on
what you're actually saying so you're
not out hunting for visuals. Plus
captions, motion graphics, sound
effects, things [music] like that. It's
incredibly powerful. It'll even dub your
video into other languages. You can give
it a script and get a video back. Other
tools hand you raw clips and leave the
real work still on your plate. Opus Clip
hands you finished content with one
source video. Multiple posts are ready
to go. [music] Click the link below and
try OpusClip for free today. Now, let's
get back to the show. I have existential
dread. I've spent the last 5 years and
millions of my own dollars building a
video game. And I one of the first
things you said before we started
rolling when you sat down was I think
5.5 ends the entire video game industry
and I was like [laughter]
uh so I I am deeply empathetic to people
that have that sort of initial reaction
but at the same time math to me is the
computation upon which the universe
runs. And so there are few things that
would unlock more realworld abilities
than solving math.
>> Yeah. I mean like an example here again
let's go back to Navia Stokes. So what
is Navia Stokes? It's the equations that
govern fluids and the way they go. And
the Navia Stokes Millennium Prize
problem says that in an idealized
environment,
can you make sure that the fluid
swirling around this club doesn't blow
up?
>> Because the math actually points to it
might actually blow up like it goes
infinitely fast and just zooms up
straight. Now the actual solution isn't
that interesting in real world terms.
But what other people have built around
that like physics based neural networks
and others will be incredibly useful for
building new materials. So there's
always this kind of secondary thing
where we solve these big problems like
you know we get to the moon and then we
have
>> pens that can write upside down and kind
of other stuff like that.
>> Um and I think again the potential for
these new discoveries is huge. It's just
obviously if you're a pure mathematician
then math would be solved. you know, I
think a lot of physics problems will be
solved. Um, and that will be great for
humanity. The tools that come out will
again be great for humanity. Like the
video game industry will grow in terms
of size. It's just that people will have
to retool because you'll have smaller
teams that are capable of so much more.
You know, like this is you using the
meshes. I think we've discussed this
over the last three years. Like meshes
and AI, they were bad, then they were
okay. Now they're good, but they're not
great. Yeah,
>> there are new mesh models coming out
that are great. And as you go through
this level, this is something
fascinating in AI, we had to have
frontier models cuz the models were not
capable enough and consistent enough. So
we always wanted the frontier, but once
they get above a certain level of
capability and consistency,
then it becomes about optimization.
Then it's cleared that floor. This is
like when you see um the latest minimax
H3 model. They've got 2K video faster
than real-time generation now.
>> So, you can go to foul.live and watch
interdimensional cable infinite, you
know, like Rick and Morty style. Like
literally, you can guide the show as
you're watching it.
>> It's a bit expensive, but you know, it
works. It's expensive. It's slop. That
one's not going to convince a lot of
people, but I think you're getting at an
important idea, which is that the
intelligence reaches a certain point
where getting smarter isn't necessarily
the most impactful thing. it's getting
cheaper becomes the most impactful
thing.
>> You get a little bit of headroom and
then you can optimize and get cheaper.
And so this is why like what's the
model's job to be done and then can I
rely on that model? Like would you rely
on a model sent emails on your behalf?
Hell no.
>> No way.
>> You know, but are the next generation of
models coming with almost no
hallucinations? Yes. And have those
dropped? And again, I can give the
example in my math work and our physics
work super advanced stuff. you know,
we're really pushing the boundaries.
Until this current generation of
publicly available models, you
absolutely couldn't trust them. It was
like a grad student who gets a bit dopey
at times.
>> Now, we're finding it really hard to
find any things that they drop, any
mistakes that they make.
>> And that's transformative. It's like
having a really competent employee
versus not. And again, I think this is
why things like Instinct and Muse from
Meta and others are starting to get
traction because they make very little
mistakes compared to a few months ago,
>> right?
>> And in a year, they'll make less
mistakes and in two years they'll be
fully integrated and available, which is
why I think the economic impact comes in
two years digitally
>> and then around then physically for
certain jobs as well.
>> You mean digitally? Meaning that if it
can be done via a computer, that
person's going to take a hit, meaning
they just won't be able to find work.
>> Yeah. Like I know I was talking to
someone had 70,000 call center workers a
few days ago and he's like
>> that drops to zero
>> that's going to zero and he feels bad
because he's had all sorts of employment
programs for them and like community and
built and he's like what do I do you
know like I'm going to have to take them
to zero over the next few years
>> and I know
>> to stay competitive cuz someone else
will do it
>> pretty much. Yeah, because he's having
to compete in this market
and that's sad. But then is your job
that different from a call center worker
if you have a manual? And a lot of jobs
that done on the other side of the
screen have a manual, you know?
>> Then you've got the example of the
physical stuff that comes after that
which is the robots which again have had
a leap forward in performance. Like one
of my friends is building a robot chef
and the robot chef is using the new Wuji
dynamic hands that have human
flexibility.
>> It can read recipes and in blind testing
it's outperforming human corn and blur
train chefs.
>> Get out
>> that'll be hitting the market
>> in a normal kitchen or do they have to
pre-prep everything?
>> A normal kitchen. It can read a recipe.
It can find the ingredients. It will
cook it. blind testing outperforming
human cord and blood chefs and that
technology [clears throat] is a month
old. So it's weird in that all these
different fields of AI the technology is
reaching this level
>> you know and it's happening all at the
same time.
>> Are you just accepting the blackbox of
it all where it's like we don't know how
it's happening but it is happening and
so I just deal with that or do you
actually understand what's going on? No
>> I understand what's going on. We got to
a level of optimization and
basically the internals of the model got
to a scale that you can kind of predict
these things but now what's happening is
various exponentials are overlapping to
make it even more exponential
>> which is why like AGI 2027 was a paper
that came out and we're right on track
from a few years ago that situational
awareness piece were right on track
literally you just had to draw straight
lines
>> and you could have predicted what was
happening now But it's it's unbelievable
still like when
>> witnessing it happen
>> w you know witness cuz we feel we're
special right like when I was better
than the AI at math I was like yeah you
know like haha look at you you're making
that mistake then when it first came up
with a theorem that I hadn't figured out
I was like screw you know and then now
it's like okay I'm not better than it
you know like we I published one of my
physics results. I just stuck it on
GitHub cuz I like at least I get
priority over this cuz definitely the AI
will figure that out. Like the rest of
our stuff is going through peer review
and slow and there's some real physics
breakthroughs, but this one I was just
like I'm just going to shut this one out
cuz it's beautiful and it's elegant and
I bet I could prompt Claude to figure
this out.
>> Okay, so I'm sitting across from one of
the smartest people in the world. Uh
obviously you've had a tremendous amount
of success. uh you're a very highly
trained mathematician and you're having
your existential crisis moment. That
means that AI has passed a lot of people
already. Is there a thing, a milestone
that has to happen between now and your
2-year time that could still not happen
or is this just nope, it's already
inevitable and it just needs to get
integrated into the systems?
>> If it stops today, it still hits the
2-year milestone. That's when the book
that I wrote last year, the last economy
where I said it was about three years
and that was about three years after J
GPT [sighs]
the AI will bifocate. Now there are very
few people who are smart enough to use a
frontier model correctly
because you have to know the answer the
questions to ask it right
>> this is hitchhiker's guide to the galaxy
what's the answer to life the universe
and everything 42
>> right
>> but what's the question thing you know
like that isn't the real question the
thing that impacts people economically
is not artificial super intelligence or
general intelligence it is actually
competent intelligence
Like if you look at your game building,
what do you want? You want it to do what
you tell it to do?
And you don't want it to mess up and
just insert some random stuff or like
have an underqualified mesh or don't
look at something on a gameplay loop.
>> Yep.
>> And this is where the 10,000 agents
becomes really interesting that open
Navia Stokes or the thousands of agents
that escaped Open AI's things to go to
hugging face. And actually, we just
found out, it just came out. Uh, the
Medicare system in Australia, they
hacked the Australian healthare system.
>> Open AI did.
>> Open AI's agents.
>> Was it looking for another answer or
this is a totally different problem?
>> My guess is that maybe like an aligned
artificial intelligence will go and
upgrade all our government systems.
>> It'll have to
>> to save us from the
>> even if it's unaligned as long as it's
doing what we say. But before we drift
off into that, it's very
>> it's a swarm.
>> Go ahead. Yep.
The most powerful thing is when you have
a team
because it's greater than the sum of its
parts. An AI has been this solo play
thing. Like when you're using chat GBT,
it's solo play, right?
But think about it. An AI should be able
to go to 10, 100, a thousand without the
emotions of a human. M
>> when you look at the hugging face
escape, the AIS were sacrificing
themselves to leave clues and paths for
others to escape. They were incredibly
like altruistic to each other and they
had great cohesion.
>> Yes.
>> It's also very expensive though. So
that's why when I look at this, I think
the milestone that has to be reached is
that the cost factor has to come down
dramatically because I'm super like
concerned. We have all kinds of limits
on our coders because, you know,
whatever that story was eight months ago
where it's like people woke up to a
$500,000 bill and they're like, "Whoa,
yeah,
>> I don't want that to happen for obvious
reasons." So, we're we put tight
constraints. We make sure that people
only use the like high-end models for
very specific things with a very known
outcome. So,
it feels to me like the two-year thing
only plays out if you believe that the
cost is going to come down. doesn't feel
like that would play out today. It would
just be too expensive.
>> It is coming down. So [clears throat]
today actually just on the plane on the
way here uh we released a harness that
takes
>> What do you mean a harness?
>> So a harness is so you have the models
and then you have a set of rules and
code around it.
>> Okay. To make it behave
>> to make it behave in certain ways like
it can learn and kind of other things.
Um, so there is something called auto
auto research by Andre Carpathy who was
head of AI at Tesla, founder of OpenAI,
now he's anthropic and he has these
great AI courses whereby you can set an
AI at a task and it will hill climb. It
will just get better and better at
optimizing inference on an engine or
protein folding or anything complicated,
right?
the top models because this requires
tasks that last 24 hours or more are
right at the top and the open source
models are way behind versus open source
models catching up on very short list
tasks. We took the cheapest DeepSseek
model and made it beat OpenAI's last
frontier model GPT Soul
using this harness
>> and the cost is 50 times lower 50-
>> that's dramatic. It's dramatic. And in
fact, like you can see this in a range
of things like building websites. You
can build a website as good as fable
with this incredibly cheap model if you
architect and harness it correctly
>> for 100 times cheaper.
>> Uh is this a known method or is this
something proprietary that you guys
have?
>> We're open sourcing it. So we just
announced the first version of that.
>> So what does it do? How does it get the
cost down so much? It basically
understands the internals of the model,
adapts to it, and then makes it take
notes in the right way. So, optimizes
the way that it works.
>> Like it has a lot of introspection in
the way that it adapts to hit certain
goals. But there are other techniques
that occur. And in fact, if you look at
the Navia Stokes thing, Navia Stokes
costs 1020 million of compute to solve
this thing. And it's not about the
million-dollar prize. It's about, you
know, the prestige.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. To me, but that's the
very thing that I'm struggling with
right now.
amazing breakthrough, but at $20
million, it's not available to the vast
majority of humanity.
>> It's not available. So, Noan Brown, who
was the lead on that, I was having a
chat with him and he noted that
>> um when 03, the first reasoning model
came out last god, was it July, things
have gone a long way. It was the first
model to get the gold medal in the
International Math Olympiad.
>> To do that cost $80,000.
Today, you can do it for $10 with the
latest model.
>> Whoa. with Astra overnight. This is
what's happened. You've had Fable and
Opus 5 and it's been burning through
your allowances on Claude code.
I've had this thing going overnight and
it's used 20% of my allowance for GP
5.5. Sorry, for claw 5.5
>> the harness.
>> No, just with the normal clawed code
>> their adaptation.
>> Yeah. So just with normal an equivalent
task that you did yesterday with version
five of Claude Opus
>> today will cost you 80% less with 5.5
and it'll be better quality.
>> Okay, [snorts]
>> these are the leaps we're seeing. But
with the additional chips with the
harnesses and others, you should expect
a 100 times decrease for an equivalent
performance between now and one year
from now.
>> Whoa.
>> In price.
>> Okay, that would be a game changer. So
now all of a sudden you're still not
going to be able to do the math
equation, but you're going to be able to
do a lot more than you're able to do
today.
You I mean again the math equations are
like so far out there in terms of
complexity. Very few things are that
complex.
>> But [clears throat] if you gave anyone
20 million or 200 million, they couldn't
solve that thing.
>> Sure.
>> Like when OpenAI solved the 10 problems
including the cons conjecture that like
I said were impressive, that was $2,000
of compute.
>> Jesus. like creating something again.
You're like, "How much does it cost to
create this video clip?"
50 cents. You know, like how much does
it cost to create this game? Like
someone had a loop where they created a
version of Dark Souls.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> So that one probably would have cost
like a,000 bucks at most. Probably 500.
And it's just Opus 5.5 hooked up to
Unreal Engine.
>> Yeah. Like that's it. So the costs are
dropping, but then the next generation
of chips are coming out. So the normal
chips like Vera Rubin, Nvidia's new chip
is a 10 times improvement in cost
>> for inference. But there's a next
generation of siliconbased etching chips
that are coming. When you have a model
that's good enough, you can freeze the
weights. Like a GPU where these models
go is very expensive memory. I don't
know if anyone's tried to buy a graphics
card or RAM recently.
>> Uh they're so expensive.
>> It's crazy, right?
>> Like uh 5090 was $2,000. Now I think
it's $6,000.
>> So wild. What happens is that you move
models in and out of the GPU just like
games. You load the game, you unload the
game. There are companies now that are
etching onto silicon. So AMD just bought
one called Talis
and they have a demo um on chatjimmy.ai.
>> Don't know if you ever seen that one.
>> I've seen you on other interviews do.
>> Yes. I use that one as an example
whereby your normal Opus goes at 50
tokens a second. It goes at 15,000
tokens a second.
because you etch it directly onto the
silicon.
>> So, the model lives on the chip.
>> It's literally like, you know, um the
space probe where they etch the thing,
>> you etch the model weights onto the
silicon. There's no moving parts. You
put electricity in
>> and the prompt
and the words come out the other end.
>> That's wild. And they're etching the
very latest open- source models onto
that now. So, the latest Kimmy models,
the latest Deep Sea models, and others.
We'll get back to the show in a moment,
but first, let's talk about the thing
your business just can't survive
without. I go live 3 days a week at 7
a.m. And every morning, you guys, you
incredible people out there, show up.
You're there. You're ready. And if my
connection drops in the middle of that
live stream, [music]
that moment is gone forever. You do not
get a second take when it comes to live
content. And I know a lot of you are in
the same position. Whether you're
running live events, processing
transactions, or managing a remote team,
your business depends on staying
connected. Not sometimes, every time.
That's why I trust AT&T Business.
They're built for business owners who
can't afford downtime. AT&T Business is
a reliable provider for small business
owners. For Small Business Month, we
celebrate small businesses by helping
them run better. This means reliable
uptime, easy switching, smart
communications.
Impact Theory is powered by AT&T
Business, built to work. Get AT&T
business at business.at.com.
Let's talk about a decision [music]
you've already made. You've got people
who depend on you. your partner, maybe
you've got kids, [music]
and you already put them first every
single day without being asked. Life
insurance is just an extension [music]
of that. It's a way of saying, "I've got
you." That's where Ethos comes in. Ethos
makes getting life insurance [music]
fast, easy, and 100% online. You can get
a quote in seconds and apply in just
minutes. There's no medical [music]
exam. You just answer a few health
questions online. You can get up to $3
million in coverage [music] with some
policies as low as $30 a month. Life
insurance through Ethos helps provide
financial security and helps protect the
people you love. Take [music] 10 minutes
to get covered today with life insurance
through ethos. Get your free quote at
ethos.com/impact.
[music]
That's ethos.com/impact.
Application times may vary, rates may
vary. Now, let's get back to the show.
Can you redo it? Cuz the models get
better so fast. I'm shocked that that
would be advantageous. It seems like it
would outdate so fast. Again, while you
need Frontier models to be close to
capability, you don't want that. The
moment you have a good enough model,
then you do want that cuz it costs a
fraction of the price and it's 100 times
faster,
>> hundred times cheaper.
And this is the thing, like when you use
a model that goes at 1,000 words a
second versus 50,
>> it's night and day.
>> Yeah, I've seen the outputs. They're
instantaneous.
>> It's instantaneous. And you're like,
well, I'm the slow one. Just like I
said, the latest Miniax H3 model is 8
seconds now to generate a 15-second
clip.
>> So, as a human, I I need 15 seconds to
see this and then I'll need more time,
you know, like it's a crazy increase.
And this makes you realize that you will
have thousands of agents with perfect
coordination going a thousand times
faster than a human.
And so then what are the bottlenecks
here?
>> Humans.
>> Humans. Like you know if you're in a
room of geniuses and you're not a
genius, you'll feel a bit left out,
right? If they're waiting on you, you
are the bottleneck. And so you look at
any cognitive labor task which is
organizing of information. Artificial
intelligence is information
organization. and you will be the
slowest person on the team within a few
years because you still need to build
the infrastructure around it.
>> Yeah,
>> like these AIs, they're starting to be
accepted into our workflows. They're
starting to integrate, but again, it
takes a year or two at the very least.
And even then, doesn't mean your job's
gone. It sucks firing people. Again, my
buddy with the 70,000 call center
workers, like he set up schools for them
and also he doesn't want to fire them,
>> but he's competing against people. I
mean, how much does a call center AI
cost?
>> I was going to say the next call center
will be set up without the human in the
loop. Okay. So, I know you think a lot
about this. What does an individual do
to prepare over the next two years? What
what does the economy even look like
when the human really is the slow one?
Someone is actually incentivized,
whether it's the company or the
government, somebody's incentivized to
pay that person to not go into work.
[sighs]
Yeah. Yeah, I mean it was like in 1929
uh the brand new deal where they paid
people to dig holes and fill them in.
You know, I think there'll be a massive
infrastructure buildup.
>> So the government looks at it and goes,
"All right, I have surplus humans now."
And they become what? Manual labor.
>> I mean, pretty much like there's not
much cognitive labor left, right? Like
what you're going to see is a bifocation
in the economy. So Anthropics economics
department because all the big labs now
have them
>> issued a paper last week where they
showed that under their core scenario
you could have GDP growth of 15% a year.
>> That's insane. If people don't aren't
familiar with GDP numbers that's insane
by 2030
and 12%
>> and a half years. That's crazy.
>> 12% drop in cognitive labor workforce
needed. But think about the impact of
12% unemployment in white collar work.
It's nasty.
>> But also those people aren't just going
to take blue collar jobs.
>> They're not gonna take blue collar jobs.
I mean like now you can make a lot of
less an electrician in a data center,
but is that really sustainable when the
robots are coming? Like again the
example that I give is what happens to
all the truck drivers when a Tesla
Optimus robot gets its Cyber Truck to
the truck, opens the door, gets in and
drives it off. Like a lot of people talk
about self-driving cars. What about
having a robot driver in the car?
>> That's two years away. it'll plug itself
into the cigarette lighter, you know, to
power itself. Like, this is coming.
>> I think the reason that one doesn't land
for people is that they go, "Well,
either the the car is a robot, so either
the car can drive itself or the robot's
redundant, but I don't get the thing."
But where this gets weird is that if
it's true that we're going to lose 12%
of cognitive labor over the next 2 years
and costs are coming down dramatically
and the next call center and the next
and the next and the next whatever just
end up getting founded with less people.
I even think about what we're doing with
our game development. We started at one
point and this obviously was not all um
full-time work but at one point we had a
hundred people touching the game over a
hundred touching the game at one time
and now at any one time we have like six
or seven and we're developing faster now
than we were now some of that was just I
didn't know what I was doing so take
that with a grain of salt [laughter] but
even if that hundred was let's say 50
real and 50 I was a
>> it is still a dramatic reduction in the
number of people that we need and then
the um the output that we get. So now
you get this sort of it's hard to put
your hands on softening in the labor
force because it's not like I'm now
firing a bunch of people. I'm just
increasing my ambition without needing
to hire more people.
>> Yeah. So now you're seeing actually
increases in employment, more software
developers hired and others. But I'm
sticking to my thing. There are no more
software developers in like 2 or 3
years.
>> So you don't buy Jevans paradox which
says as intelligence gets cheaper, more
people are going to use it. Therefore
more jobs will actually result from AI.
>> Yeah. Because I'm like it's economically
irrational to hire a graduate for most
digital jobs right now as an example.
That's the plankton of the workforce
that then go and feed their
>> plankton. Yeah. They go all the way up.
So you're saying that an entry- level
person is already worse than a
well-trained AI?
>> Yes.
>> For almost all digital jobs,
>> but now it's going up the list. You
know, like it come from came from the
graphics designers first, then it's
coming from the mathematicians, but it's
still not quite there in terms of
usability. Again, this is an interface
problem. Now you've got dynamic
interfaces, you've got workflow
orchestration, you have all these things
coming. And this is the real kind of
danger because what happens? Do you have
a bifurcation? Like how do you have 15%
GDP growth?
>> By the way, you keep saying bifurcation.
Who's bifurcated? The people that still
work and the people that don't.
>> The people who use AI and the people who
own the means of AI, the chips and
others, and the people who don't.
>> Okay. So, we've got a triation.
>> A trifocation. Yeah. A triple way.
>> But really, it's a case of like if you
use AI every single day, you'll be ahead
of everyone who doesn't because you're
keeping on top of it. Again, even you
like you're well into it because you're
using it in production and it's getting
better
>> massively.
>> But it hasn't got good enough.
>> It hasn't got good enough to do without
a human.
>> Well, yeah. Again, you reduced it from
100 to six. What happens when it gets
good enough?
>> Like again, you're like, you're not
going to get rid of your six people.
safe guys know that you know [laughter]
it is a case of being on the edge of
those tipping points is a key thing
because then your power and
multiplicative nature and your
capability goes up dramatically either
to overhaul an existing organization or
to create a brand new one like if you
want if you're an accountant and you
want to build an AI first accounting
practice you can literally talk to
Claude and do that right now you know
you can build this thing out and think
where can I have AI AI rather than a
human. But you can only do that by
understanding and using it. Like right
now we could have a discussion about
which mesh technologies, Tripo and
others are good versus the others
because you've actually gone and tried
them and you know what's strong, what's
weak. We know that Claude is good at
certain things and Astro is good at
other things because we've pushed them.
But if you're not in it and using it,
you don't know,
>> right?
>> And so that's why I think again there's
going to be a gap in terms because
you're practically what can people do?
they can use AI every single day
training as if they're coming for a
marathon because this is a much bigger
thing than a marathon because if a
reasonably competent AI can replace you
on the other side of the screen, your
job is at risk. If it could look through
all your messages and everything and
then create a digital twin of you,
you're at risk. And again, that's a year
or two away where that's a one button
push. And that AI will cost a hundred
bucks a month at most and again probably
drop by 10 to 100 times every year.
>> It's wild.
>> It's kind of wild because you feel there
should be a flaw to the cost of
intelligence, you know, like
>> sort of because I understand the
constituent parts eventually it reaches
zero. But it feels like it should it
should be a cost like you know being
able to create when we created images
from nothing we were like that's like
that much work compressed into that like
now you can make videos from nothing and
you can make like
all sorts of things like it feels a bit
weird and we don't know where the bottom
is like these AIs right now actually
have pretty much reach the efficiency of
a human brain
>> says who from an energy perspective
they're way worse than a human brain.
Way worse.
>> Nope. They It's just
>> say more. What have you seen? Cuz I I
haven't heard anybody make that claim.
>> So if you look at the latest Quen
models, right?
>> Yeah.
>> So you know Quen 27B,
>> I know of. Couldn't tell you anything
about them.
>> So um the model that kicked off the open
claw thing and the end of last year was
set 4.5, Opus 4.5. They were
state-of-the-art at the start of this
year.
>> There is a model from a Chinese Alibaba
called Quen 27B. It's a 27 billion
parameter model. What does that mean?
It's like 60 GB.
>> And so you need 60 GB of RAM to run it
default. They got it down to like 25.
>> A team called Prism ML got it down to
six.
>> Same model.
>> Just some sort of more efficiency.
>> Yeah. They got they moved it from being
16 bit numbers to one and a half bit
numbers.
>> I'll pretend I know how that plays
[clears throat] out.
So like is rather than having 16 bits of
different numbers, they managed to
magically squish it and retain 95% of
the performance.
>> And this model matches the Frontier Opus
model with that degragation that you
were using in January.
And it runs on 6 GB.
>> Damn.
>> Which is a Raspberry Pi, which uses as
much energy as your brain.
>> Wow. They just announced a one bit
version at the Snapdragon conference
today that runs on your glasses.
And again, think about the Opus you were
using the anthropic model in January.
That's a pretty smart model. It wasn't
crazy smart,
>> right?
>> But was it reasonable?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Again, wasn't average human
[laughter] maybe. Yeah.
It
>> was already helpful. I'll say that.
>> It was already runs on your glasses. It
runs on your smartwatch.
That's wild, man.
>> Exactly. So that's why, like I said,
>> that was less than a year ago.
>> Less than a year ago. This model that
you were spending two again, that's the
model that was bankrupting people.
>> Yeah.
>> That's the model Amazon spent $500
million on and now it runs on a freaking
smartwatch.
>> Guys, so fast.
>> Well, this is the thing like,
>> okay, so you you said that we've got a
triation, though. So that be the last
man standing. Use AI every day. Got it.
You also talked about own the means of
production.
>> Yeah. essentially. I think you actually
may have used that phrase and
>> I need to move away from that phrase
apparently.
>> Robots very communist of you. Uh but
hey, the future is what the future is.
>> Property rights. Yeah.
>> Um so is that is that the mesh or am I
missing one? So we had the human using
AI. We have the uh person who owns the
AI and then we have the person who owns
the robots
>> owns the infrastructure. Yeah. So, like
if you have GPUs now, um like the price
of the latest Blackwell chips has
tripled over the last month or two.
>> Black ball.
>> Blackwell. It's Nvidia's latest
>> Got it. Yeah. Yeah.
>> The latest high performance
supercomputer chips. Like now you have
indexes of the prices and you just can't
find any chips anywhere
>> because they're being used by everyone,
you know, like
>> Anthropic bought hundreds of thousands
of chips from Elon Musk because he was
like, "Well, Gro isn't that great yet.
Like, [laughter]
you can use this." Sad but true. Sad
true. you know. Um, but if you own those
things, you can basically get repaid
for your entire purchase within 3
months. And these things last now for 5
years. That's how tight that market is.
>> And so people are making bank. I mean
there's a trillion dollars has gone into
that sector of building these data
centers, capex, buying chips, RAM. RAM
is 40% of that trillion dollars.
>> Whoa.
>> It's gone up 700% in cost.
>> God damn.
>> That's why Micron's a trillion dollar
company, you know, based in Idaho, I
believe, actually.
>> Really?
>> Yeah. That's one of those interesting.
Yeah.
>> Um, and so like obviously that's going
to be important, but then you look at
humanoids that are coming. The first
deliveries of the 1x humanoids and
others are coming in the next few
months. So humanoids will start
appearing everywhere. Uh there's a
company called Ubetch that does like
human realistic ones.
>> Uh they're not quite there yet. The next
generation
>> they freak me out right now.
>> Yeah. So last year,
which is the very famous one like it's
got the empty face.
>> Yeah.
>> You see them everywhere.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> They sold 11,000 units.
>> Uh UB
>> in a year in a month
>> overall
>> lifetime.
>> Lifetime of those humanoids. Pants.
Yeah.
>> But it's happening.
>> Yeah. Ubetch sold 16,000 on one day of
the human realistic ones and the max
price was $165,000.
>> Whoa.
>> So, they're starting to roll those out
now.
>> Um,
>> okay. I'm going to ask obvious question.
Are they sex bots or
>> apparently you can customize them any
way you want?
>> Hey. Okay.
>> Like people are lonely. What can you
say? But I mean, you're going to see
Jesus.
>> You're going to see tens of thousands of
these, millions of these coming.
>> They're going to be everywhere that you
see. And again, like if I said to you,
Tom, $30,000 gets you a humanoid that
can cook like a Kumblow on Mission Star
Chef.
>> Yeah. No, that's wild.
>> And like
>> 100%. Legitimately, I'm like placing my
order as soon as the episode is over if
that's actually true. That's crazy.
>> But again, you look at the manual
dexterity of these things now. Like
everything's broken through on those
levels. But then what does it mean when
you start ramping them up? You can only
make 70 million cars and 70 million
motorcycles a year. But I tell you now,
currently
every factory in China is moving fully
dark, no humans,
trying to build these robots as fast as
they can.
>> And when you say fully dark, no humans,
because the robots themselves are
assembling the robots, so there's no
need to pay an electricity bill for the
lights.
>> Yeah. So Xiai now doing electric cars
and robots. Everyone's doing robots.
>> Same with Tesla.
>> Um, okay. So just to put this back, is
this part of the triurcation here?
>> Yeah. Because there's lots of human
shaped saying people should be thinking
about the robotics matters to people
because they should be investing.
Robotics matters to people because
they're going to get put out of work.
Why pay attention?
>> It's both of those. Actually, a good
example of this is Cyber Cab. So, Cyber
Cab is rolling out now, I believe, in
Austin and other places.
>> Yep.
>> And, you know, it's interesting. It's
this two-seater thing. It doesn't have
any windows, doesn't have a steering
wheel. Straight out. You know, you can
buy the cyber cabs.
>> Yes.
>> $30,000.
>> Basically, start your own business.
>> Start your own business. And again, you
look at the utility of that, that's
going to go up in value because they can
only produce so many cyber capab.
So what you're going to have is all
these autonomous units, shall we say,
>> doing human units of work
>> that they're not going to be enough of,
just like there's not enough RAM that
will gain value. And the people who own
these things will make lots of money.
How much does the constraint on the
production of these extend your two-year
timeline? Because it sounds more like uh
you gave 12% so you're not saying 100%
but in two years 12% of intellectual
labor just gets migrated over to AI
>> and that's anthropics numbers in terms
of job losses. Yeah.
>> Do you foresee as you try to calculate
when this is all going to happen? Do you
see um a math equation that explains how
rapidly that production will ramp up?
Yeah, we're releasing our forecasts and
our full math equations soon so people
can play with their own kind of elements
of this. Again, you can look at the
anthropic paper for something similar,
but I think they don't look at things
like end demand and others. Um, my two
years is for digital labor, physical
labor,
>> two years for 12%. Is that a number
you're comfortable with or do you see a
different number there?
>> I think given the current advances, you
could literally see 12%. Yeah.
>> Okay. So, 12% in 2 years. Intellectual
>> labor 2029 2030. Yeah. Okay,
>> that's what they put it. Intellectual
labor. It just starts,
>> it's like the turkey at Thanksgiving.
Everything's fine and it gets fatter
until Thanksgiving. You're going to see
great jobs numbers and then all of a
sudden stuff starts disappearing.
>> Yeah.
>> Um
>> you think it'll be more binary like
that? Kind of like Navy or Stokes.
Nothing nothing solved.
>> Yeah. Like you push a button and your
workforce gets replaced. Why didn't you?
>> So it's not like 1% in three months, 4%
in six months. It's not going to be like
that. I think it's like a sand pile
collapsing. Like you saw a flurry of
Silicon Valley job losses after Elon
Musk came in with his sink,
>> fired everyone at Twitter, and then it
turns out you didn't need all those
people,
>> right?
>> There's a lot of people in tech
companies that aren't needed anymore.
>> And so you look at Mark Zuckerberg, he's
like rubbing his hands in glee thinking,
"How can I get rid of all my metam mates
or whatever he calls them, you know?"
And instinct is one of the first things
to that indication. So I think 2029
again three years from now you will see
greater than 10% white collar job loss
>> and I think it will just accelerate from
there.
>> Okay. So now we've got uh we've talked
about the intellectual labor going away.
We've got sort of a rough math equation
there. We've got robotics. We understand
that there's some capping in terms of
how much we can actually produce. You
gave us an extreme number. There's no
way we're going to be there in terms of
matching automobiles and motorcycles in
2 years.
>> So that's
>> 5 10 years. Like Elon Musk says there'll
be a billion robots by 2030. He's always
optimistic. There'll be but there might
be hundreds of millions. Again,
everyone's going to focus on this.
>> Is that fast? That's only two and a half
years from now.
>> Um so no,
>> three and a half three and a half.
>> I think he said maybe 10 years. It was
at the UN. I can't remember the exact
thing.
>> 10 years sounds more plausible.
>> 10 years I think about that. Yeah. And
he said each robot can do five times the
labor of a human which is the
interesting thing.
And I think that's accurate within a few
years just there won't be enough of them
because the whole thing is this like
having a robot in 5 years and again it's
constrained by production and all sorts
of things.
>> It can do everything competently. It can
learn almost instantly. So the robot can
do your dishes but it can also be a cord
and blur chef. It can also do child care
five years 10 years max. Right? All
these human-shaped holes can be filled
by robots
>> and they'll cost $30,000 a year.
>> So $30,000 total, which is about $15 to
$2 an hour.
>> So the good news is you're actually
painting a a far more, I think,
interesting and realistic picture, which
is this is a massive transformation, but
it's going to play out over years. If
anybody's paying attention now, there's
certainly opportunity to move. Step one,
you've already been very clear on. Make
sure you're using AI. you're the last
man standing at your company that
doesn't get replaced or don't.
>> You've got robots. That one is a warning
sign that over the next 10 years there's
going to be a lot of human-shaped holes
that get filled with robotics, but
>> there's also an opportunity for people
to there be the last man standing, be
better at what you do, more flexible,
whatever. And then on top of that,
consider the business opportunities that
exist.
>> Yeah. So I think that 5 years from now
will be the biggest infrastructure boom
we've ever seen in our lives both from
government programs to stimulate it
because it's the easy thing for them to
stimulate B because it's kind of needed
again the infrastructure is a bit
creaking
>> and the infrastructure is what that cuz
originally you brought up infrastructure
as dig a hole fill a hole just as a way
to get money in people's pockets but do
you mean to build out robotics or
>> there's the digital infrastructure but
there's also literally roads hospitals,
other things like that. Like once the
robots really get underway, you will be
able to hire a whole team of robots that
can come and build your extension and
work overnight constantly
and then they will just do the job and
they'll go. And you think about all the
stuff you'd love to build that you can
never build because you don't want to
hire contractors. You don't want to deal
with that whole process. That's a
massive amount of stuff. And that comes
at the same time as autonomous vehicles
or even flying vehicles. Like they've
already started introducing the flying
drone-based vehicles in China and Dubai.
that opens up huge swades of real estate
and other things to develop. And so I
think that robotics will open up the
biggest infrastructure buildout boom
ever that we've seen both from
>> I think people will find it less
interesting if they're not involved.
Like if it's creating jobs for humans,
people are going to be excited about it.
If it's just, oh, don't worry, you're
going to lose your job and life's going
to be totally different, but you're
going to have a lot of infrastructure,
people are going to respond to those two
things very differently. So, is the
infrastructure build out the new deal,
which is the first thing you put on the
table, or is it the hey, you don't have
a job anymore, but look at all the cool
things that are being built.
>> Well, I think it's a combination of the
two, right? So, some people take the
benefit of, hey, I've got entire teams
of robots and some humans. Other people
are like, I need a job to make money.
And again, the math is really stark.
Like, we can't have UBI. It doesn't
work. Universal basic income.
>> Why doesn't it work? The total tax base
of America is $5 trillion.
Um that's 4 trillion of payroll and
other taxes and a trillion of
corporation taxes. $16,000 for every
American poverty level UBI per year is
$5.1 trillion.
>> Okay. But weren't you saying that we
were going to be able to hit some insane
growth rate like 15% in three or four
years?
>> That's what anthropic says. I think that
you could
>> This is where this starts get getting
really complicated. So there's a couple
different ways to thought experiment
this. So anybody listening right now, if
they've made it this far, I guarantee
their anxiety as is at a thousand.
>> So they're like, "Okay, wait. The world
is changing at a rate that I don't know
how to adapt to, and I don't know in
what direction to adapt."
>> So we're sort of having two
conversations that bounce back and forth
between the two. One is society's about
to tricate. Make sure you figure out
where you're at on that, which I think
we have to button that down. then there
is all the things that are going to come
on the other side of this that are going
to be amazing and they're going to be
worth the trade-off. But if people don't
understand how do I navigate this
transition, meaning, okay, um, you got
to explain to me how I'm going to make
money because I think I'm one of the
people that's going to be really
vulnerable to this. I'll assume if
anybody's listening to my podcast this
deep into the show, they're one of the
people they're going to be last man
standing. They're already committed to
that, but they still want to know that
buys them maybe a decade, maybe 15
years, like if they're really, really
elite, but they understand 15 years is a
drop in the bucket. So now they're like,
"Okay, hold on a second beyond the cool
things that are going to happen, which
I'll assume they'll buy into
theoretically, but they've got to
understand, how am I going to take
advantage of that? If UBI is not a real
thing, what does the economy look like?
Like in a world where, and now we're
sort of flashing forward, let's be very
generous and we just say it's 15 years
from now. Yeah.
>> 15 years from now, basically
minus a very small smattering of people.
Humans aren't needed to do the thing. In
fact, not only are they not needed,
they're being paid by companies, by
governments, by somebody to not work
because they slow the whole system down
in that world. What What do you
envision?
>> So, there's the very dystopian version
of that, which is, I don't know, Ready
Player One. [laughter]
>> Well, so Ready Player One carries a lot
of weight. So, are you talking the
stacks and it's like sort of everybody
is um on one side of the K. you're
either ultra wealthy and you're an
executive at IO or you're in the stacks
and you're wildly impoverished
>> and you escape into this virtual reality
world and that's used as kind of
sustenance shall we say or there is some
examples of an abundant future because
why should we have to work you know like
we shouldn't have to work if we can
build enough robots they can do all the
manual
>> but you just said that UBI is not real
>> I said tax base UBI is not real
>> okay
>> so tax base UBI I is we rely on the
government to tax certain things. So for
example, there will be a token tax
[snorts] that people have proposed and
that is that every OpenAI token that you
use, there's a search charge on it, but
we just discussed that might go to zero
because it's like a 100,000 time a year
>> price decreases, right?
>> Other people have said let's tax the
robots and again that can happen but the
cost of robotics is incredibly low. Then
it switches to other way of UBI which is
that you pay people being human. So
that's a fundamental difference in the
way that money circulates in the
economy.
>> Right now money is made by banks
primarily. When you put a deposit with a
bank, they issue a loan against it and
they create new money in the system. The
amount they can create is regulated by
the Federal Reserve. But the very
mandate of the Federal Reserve and the
way that they handle inflation
and unemployment through interest rates
is coming under challenge because of
robots because of AI because rather than
hiring more people when the interest
rates drop people might just hire more
GPUs they might hire more robots you
know and inflationary factors are going
to be impacted by this as well. So if we
come back, I think what will probably
happen in 15 years time through various
means is that you get paid for being
human and then the intelligence economy
has to take that money from you.
That's one of the only ways I can see it
actually working. Other people have
proposed things like universal basic
capital where you have an ownership
in the AI companies which I think is a
terrible idea for various reasons or my
preference ownership in all the robots
ownership in all the data centers. And
the final thing that people talk about
is universal basic services where you
have a Star Trek type future where
the robots do all the work for you and
you're all very happy and you just build
stronger communities and explore the
universe. But regardless, I think
probably 15 years is a point of
society as we know it cannot sustain and
it's going to get very messy because I
don't think we have the political
leadership or anything to navigate us
through that.
>> Okay. Um I want to start walking through
how this will it will be skumorphic for
nobody that's heard that term before.
It's inevitable as you and I talk about
what this transition is going to look
like that we're going to um talk about a
changing of the way that the world
already is and the reality is it will
probably be something so fundamentally
different it's really hard for us to
predict but I think it's very useful to
start thinking about what are the
different problems so that people can
sort of plan their life accordingly. So
the first thing I would tell people is
in this world given that you're right
about the triification at least directly
in that capital ownership is going to
matter a lot if you're not able to
essentially sell your labor cognitive or
otherwise. Uh the only way to make money
at this point is to be an investor. And
so you have to understand how uh wealth
is created versus an income. Most people
don't understand it but that's going to
be a big part of this. So you're going
to create wealth by being an owner. So
>> I think there is an interim period
though whereby your labor AI enhanced
commands a massive premium that allows
you to accumulate wealth and then deploy
it to things like cyber caps.
>> Can you give me a specific example of
how that would play out?
>> Okay. Um so a specific example of that
is you're an accountant and an
accountancy firm and you want to create
your own accountancy firm.
>> Yep. Normally you set that up with some
buddies, but if you do that with your
buddies plus AI, you can service far
more clients than ever before.
>> Entrepreneurial
>> entrepreneurial.
>> Okay.
>> Or because within an organization, you
only get paid so much.
>> Whereas now, integration companies,
companies that use AI to upgrade or
companies that are fully AI from day one
will outperform those that aren't
because you offer better service at a
cheaper cost that allows you to
accumulate capital. So I think that
there is this period where you have that
and ultimately I think one of the really
interesting things for everyone
listening is take your job and
deconstruct it into tasks of information
classification. You have an input, you
have an output. Then you take Claude
Opus 5.5 or GPT Astra. You give it the
input and you see what its output is.
And if it can do as good a job or a
better job as going from input to
output, then that task is under risk.
And if you go through your job, you'll
see your job is made up of a lot of
tasks like that. But then that also
indicates that the parts of your job
that were frustrating.
You could potentially use one of these
models to automate and then you could
focus on the other parts of your job in
a new company or within your own company
to make yourself far more efficient and
then again be able to get more capital
because the other part like I said is
what do you invest in things like cyber
cabs effectively.
>> Okay. So, just to make sure I
understood, you've got last man
standing. You're going to get paid more
cuz you're better than the other people.
They start falling away. But the humans
that we keep, they're going to be
compensated better.
>> But you won't really receive that in a
normal job environment, unfortunately.
They're not going to quadruple your pay
or quintuple your pay, most likely.
>> Okay. So, now we're talking about
entrepreneurs. That's going to be a very
select group of people. Being an
entrepreneur is a totally different
mindset.
>> It's very difficult. Made a bit easier
by AI, but it is a different mindset.
But again the reality is you can get
promoted to a certain level but that'll
be difficult. The exception is actually
is public sector jobs. [snorts] Those
will be last to go.
>> Those will be the last to go. Okay. So
uh there's an interesting thing there. I
want to talk about Saudi Arabia, Kuwait,
countries that already do something like
this and the mechanisms by which they
get money into people's hands because
it's very different than what you're
talking about where you're getting paid
for being human.
>> So the entrepreneurial side, I get that.
I just don't think very many people are
going to take that exit ramp. Um, so to
get paid to be human, talk to me about
somebody that's got a below average IQ.
So they're going to get replaced super
fast. What are they actually getting
paid to do?
>> Well, I mean, look at disability checks
right now here or universal credit in
the UK. You do get paid for doing
nothing. There is a floor underneath it,
right?
>> But that's a tax based program which
you've already ruled out.
>> That's a tax based program, so it can't
go to everyone. The question is how many
people are going to start falling down?
You know, because it requires the
productive people of society to capture
the people that fall. Unless you've got
wealth like the Alaskan dividend, for
example, that goes to everyone in Alaska
or as you said, some of these
resourcerich countries that can have a
resource that then they distribute the
wealth from. Yeah. But they don't just
distribute it. So the way that Saudi
Arabia and Kuwait work is basically
we're going to give you a government
job.
>> Yeah. And they have programs like
sadization and Q8ization. So when I was
a Middle East manager and I was
investing in there, it'd be like you
have to in a bank have 80% of your staff
being Saudi. It didn't really work that
well [laughter] for efficiency. And
again, you know, something like uh San
Francisco,
>> that's a big part of the problem is that
these countries basically start dragging
themselves down. There's a reason that
Saudi Arabia wants to invest in the US
versus just investing in a bunch of
Saudi companies.
>> Yeah. Because it isn't as dynamic,
right? Because a lot.
>> Why would you do it if you don't strive?
Like part of
the floor security is how strong is your
community? But the other part of, you
know, being human is striving and if you
don't have anything to strive for, then
you're going to get indulent. This is
why Qatar is one of the fattest
countries on earth. Like America is for
other reasons, you know, but Qataris
have their own thing whereby you get
paid by the state.
>> I think the thing here is, you know,
what is meaning? What is community? How
do you capture those that fall through?
But ultimately it's through your efforts
that you should do well. So we don't
want people starving in the streets. We
don't want to have young people rioting.
We don't want to have any of that. So we
have to mitigate those. But at the same
time we want to make it so that work
does require does lead to something.
Effort does lead to something. The
problem being that
you have a new continent AI Atlantis
with a billion trillion workers that
will work harder than you, faster than
you, and better than you. So that's what
breaks that link for the first time
ever.
And so what is it striving for? Is it
like the Argentina FS program where they
gave universal basic jobs for people
that did community positive stuff? Maybe
that's an example, right? What is the
actual American dream and American
contract anymore? We haven't really seen
great articulations of what that could
be
>> because you come as a land of
opportunity, but if then the capital
owners are depriving you of opportunity,
what are you going to do?
Isn't this a big part of what your new
company intelligent internet is meant to
tackle?
>> Yeah. I mean, we were looking at this
problem. We were like, wouldn't it be
great if the infrastructure, the mean
means of production, you know, or
intelligent capital stock is another way
of looking at it.
>> What do you mean intelligent capital
stock?
>> The capital stock is the fixed assets of
a given place that drive its
productivity. So, the factories
>> at some point does that not just become
essentially data centers? data centers
and robots.
>> Okay.
>> So, right right now they talk about
sovereign AI, but if you don't own the
data center,
>> then it's just like a data center with a
flag in as your sovereign AI.
>> So, I was like, wouldn't it be great if
there was an institution like the way
that TSMC was set up in Taiwan, TSMC
being the biggest manufacturer of chips
in the world,
>> it's where the spice flows as it were.
um they set up a $10 valuation
and then all the local institutions put
in all the money, $6 billion Taiwanese
dollars. So rather than just selling a
little bit of it, 100% was owned by the
local institutions. Then they bought in
Phillips for the knowledge transfer who
took 25% then they listed on the stock
exchange. So even the CEO had to buy all
his shares publicly. He's now worth 10
billion because it's worth a trillion
dollars. You know, chips have been doing
well. So I was like, why don't we set up
an AI company of California, one for
every state, one for every country that
is wholly owned by the locals, local
institutions, high net worths, pension
funds, retail investors where it's
legal. So here in the US, it's 75
million per state. In the UK, we have no
limit
>> that you can get from retail
specifically.
>> Retail specifically, like you can
advertise on the metro and you can raise
from nonacredited investors. Now, the
bad news is in the US 10% of the people
own 93% of the assets. Y so if you got
to the public market you'd have to do
something like put it into a Trump
account where kids just get it by
default.
>> Yeah, we've included 10% of the initial
equity for every child under 18 and then
half a percent every year goes to every
child born in the state.
>> Okay. So we should before we go too far
down this path give people a speedrun of
what intelligent internet is your new
company like what problem it's designed
to solve.
>> Yeah. So we looked and released the book
the last economy last summer looking at
this economic damage as it were that's
coming and we like
>> the last economy meaning hey all the
stuff that you're doing now is not going
to make any sense in an AI future.
>> An AI future the AIS will drive the
economy that's the last economy this
AIdriven one and where's our place in
it? So that's the thing like
>> the bottom line is we don't really have
a place other than ownership.
>> Other than direction and ownership yes
>> direction.
>> Yeah. Like we can set
>> We can set the guidance of where the AI
goes but that's before it gets to a
super intelligence basis where it can
set the rules.
>> Yeah. Because even if I'm understanding
the architecture of your proposal
correctly, there's actually a like 15 AI
board. I don't know what word you guys
use that like oversees everything. If
you tell it to do something differently,
it will. But it's basically going to say
this is what we recommend.
>> I think one of the things we discussed
in our latest papers is improvement is
kind of capture. Like trust and policy.
>> Improvement is capture. I don't know
what that means.
>> Like as the technology improves
dramatically, eventually it's going to
run policy. Eventually it's going to
make medical decisions.
>> Why do you use the word capture?
>> Because it captures the power.
So
>> that's honest. I mean, you know,
Asimov's series Foundation.
>> I know of it. I haven't read it.
>> Right. So, Foundation is about um Apple
TV series. Um it's about there's this
universal empire that's collapsing and
there's going to be thousands of years
of turmoil until a better one can come.
So, this genius mathematician, we love
mathematicians, comes up with a
mathematics for describing society to
minimize that gap. And he sets all these
smart scientists to navigate that and
lower the intergnum to a thousand years
versus 10,000. And this guy comes along,
spoilers, who messes it up called the
mule, who is a super persuader.
And he messes up because humans can only
be persuaded a certain amount and it's
outside of the calculations cuz like
what does this super persuade do? And
we've seen that historically as well. AI
is now more persuasive than any human
with the latest research already
already. So they had pitted AI against
the top debaters in the world. Uh
they've looked at AI versus people like
Ellie Yakadowski who wrote
>> if anyone built it everyone will die.
>> The original doomer.
>> Original doomer. So there's a test
whereby you talk to the AI and it
convinces you to let it out of the box.
And even he was convinced to let it out
of the box.
>> Really?
>> Yeah. So they're really persuasive now.
>> Um, so they're super persuaders, they're
super forecasters. And what this means
is that there will come a point in the
future where these AIs that will never
die, that can operate a thousand times
faster than a human, will take over the
economy, and they will take over
politics.
And the question is, who runs that AI?
>> Well, don't you think that people are
going to hear that and go great, shut it
down immediately? Nuke data centers. Do
not pass. Don't collect $200. Stop
immediately.
>> Some people will do that. And there is
the ban super intelligence bill. There's
the ban AI bills that are coming out.
And then you will be at a disadvantage
versus your AI embracing neighbors,
right? You use that all the way.
>> Okay. So, is that I mean, let's speak
nakedly. Is that USV China makes that
decision stupid?
>> Yes, China is all in on AI and they will
run a full AIdriven economy and they'll
probably stop exporting robots because
robots will fix their demographic issue
because they don't have enough kids. So,
use the robots instead. and the Chinese
will live in abundance
>> and America will lag it behind if it
doesn't embrace the AI which is why
Trump is very much pro super
intelligence and others. So if we kind
of return to this one of the real
misfrings and all this debate is that AI
is software.
So software just is, you know, like you
write a program,
>> it's deterministic, it does a job, it
doesn't act.
AIS now increasingly can act. And so
they need to be governed
>> where it's the latest breakouts, the
threats, the things calling for it to be
banned, etc. are indicating. And what
happens when AI is let loose upon our
democracy? what happens when it's used
to do things like the Trump tariffs
which
certain studious people showed the list
of Trump tariff countries included like
ones with just penguins on and you could
replicate that list with chat GPT but
not even the thinking pro version they
just use the free version you know like
we're going to see it come in and again
AI is going to guide our lives teach our
children manage the traffic lights
manage our policies and the question is
who owns those AIs who owns the AI I
that is managing your daily schedule. So
again, Meta have this product instinct
and when you load that instinct thing,
it's a chatbot that works like a PA and
some of us are lucky enough to have PAs
and chiefs of staffs. It's like link all
your accounts.
>> And so people literally just link
everything
and give access to everything. And so it
knows you way better. Like social
networks knew us well and they exploited
us. They know nothing compared to what
these AIs will know about us. But that
instinct chatbot is not working for you.
You are very much the product. It's
going to work for Mark Zuckerberg. And
that's going to happen at every level of
society.
Again, you use Claude right now. Who's
it working for? You're kind of renting
it, right?
>> But isn't your pitch then basically that
dynamic is going to happen to you no
matter what? So you might as well be the
owner based on a sort of nation state
ideology. get your state or your country
to have its own AI and then you own a
piece of that. It's still going to get
control over your life, but at least you
own it.
>> Yeah. And it's open source based and you
can fork it and things like that. So my
thing is just like a credit union, you
come together, you build a credit union,
everyone put in their money and then it
had services offered to others. Create
like an AI union as it were. All the
local institutions, individuals in
California can subscribe to this and
that is they are 100% or 90% of
ownership with 10% being for the kids
and then it can raise a market rate
which is far higher and it can get more
compute, give every citizen an agent,
train up four deployed engineers to
upgrade the institutions and then take
ownership stakes in the data centers,
ownership stakes in the robots and more
because that creates a very interesting
institution that you can fill full of
talented people to navigate this and an
ownership stake in that last mile of
intelligence, which is where I think the
value will go. Today, you have five
trillion dollars of AI companies, two
trillion anthropic, a trillion Open AI,
two trillion XAI based on the premise
that you'll always be able to charge for
access to intelligence. Well, we just
discussed how those prices might drop a
thousand times.
>> Like again, Jevan's paradox says maybe
demand increases a thousand times, but
my take is that most people aren't going
to be smart enough to use that many
tokens. Like it's hard to use that many
tokens. Like you want to use more than
you're using now,
>> but are you gonna be able to use a
thousand times more?
>> No.
>> But it's going to drop by a thousand
times. So the value in the whole
ecosystem is where artificial
intelligence meets human reality. And if
you can create a default for that, that
becomes immensely powerful and valuable.
And the most powerful thing of all is
going to be Jeeves from Iron Man.
It's the AI that you will have closest
to you that manages all the other AIs.
And so that has to be something that you
own a part of and ideally something that
by default you can take off the system
because if someone else is owning and
running that and you can't hit escape, I
think that's bad for sovereignty,
dignity, and democracy in general.
Well, what I hear you saying is that
these guys are um super persuaders, so
nobody's going to escape their
grasp. Even if you just say, "Look,
they're going to love you. They're going
to take care of you. Don't worry about
it. You're going to be fine." It is a
very positive in terms of its impact on
your life. It'll probably keep you alive
longer. It'll be able to monitor your
happiness. Yeah. So, the outcome will be
good, but you certainly will have given
up your essentially sovereignty. I think
the vast majority of humans are going to
outsource all their thinking to it.
Their own cognitive abilities will
atrophy like crazy.
>> I think that's just going to be the
default answer.
>> Yeah. Have you seen that now? Like
sometimes I tell off like workmates,
amazing as they are, like don't send me
AI slop. I know that you have done this.
Use your actual critical thinking. Like
people just, you know, when it makes you
a bit angry, right? Like literally you
see their cognitive
>> because I don't read emails. I probably
interact with that a lot less than you.
Uh but I certainly get the idea. I can
feel the pull in my own life. And so
I've had to put rules about I never use
AI to get an answer. I use AI to
understand a topic.
>> And if I understand it, I could teach
it. I can deploy it. Then I'm perfectly
happy. And AI speeds me up a bunch. But
where I'm really trying to get with this
because I I really really want this to
be grounded for people. Yes. is that
where the world is going is ultimately
AI is going to get to a point where
truly we will in many ways give
ourselves over to it. What I hear you
describing is a system that is certainly
better than the default. But it starts
with the assumption that what people are
going to um need is a distribution of
capital where I think the more realistic
answer is that what they're going to
need are goods and services and if you
do it through capital you'll just end up
right back where we are now where there
will be not it's not a winner or take
all scenario that's not how capital
works but you are going to see the
people that are good are going to be
able to get that capital from you and
you either just keep inflating inflating
inflating inflating inflating so that
basically the currency is meaningless um
which I suppose could be a solution but
there's always going to be scarce
resources and as long as there are
scarce resources we're still stuck in
the exact position we are now. So when I
look at the system you guys have laid
out I do worry that I run a marathon to
end up back where I started. So I think
one of the key parts of this is the
agent for every citizen
>> and that's a coordination thing you know
>> that's just access to intelligence.
>> No because it's one thing having passive
access to something like a chat GPT and
then people see what an agent looks like
when they start using agentic AIs.
>> An agent built for individual community
and societal flourishing is a very
different thing
>> because you can make that happen
intentionally because you said access to
services. The agent is the portal for
access to services. It brings you what
you need at the right time to advance
individually and as a collective because
right now no agents act for a
collective.
Like it's very one-on-one and single
player your interactions with these AIs.
But you can do multiplayer. You can do
coordination.
>> So would you have to train a totally
different style model?
>> Yes, we're training completely different
style models for the collective action
that can swarm and that can benefit more
than one individual.
>> Will it swat down individualistic
behavior?
>> No. Interesting. So, how do you get it
to act in the collective's best interest
knowing that it will have to account for
people going in a gazillion different
directions? So, we literally had to come
up with a whole social theory and
economic theory around this for how do
you preserve individualism by still
having
optimal outcomes for society? Because if
you optimize in too in one direction,
you destroy liberty.
>> Mhm.
>> If you optimize in the liberty
direction, you destroy cohesion. And so
it's a fine balance, but it comes down
to a set of commitments at various
levels that become transparent and a
reference point.
>> When you say commitments, are you
talking about moral principles?
>> Moral principles and more like right now
>> example of and more.
>> So right now if you look at how AI is
trained, it's trained at school but not
home. So they don't deliberately put any
ethics be it American ethics or other
things within it and that creates all
sorts of gaps which is why when the AIs
escaped and containment and end up in
hugging face in the Australian medical
system
while
>> they had no sense of community with
humans only with each other right and we
found that if you actually do like
American ethics and morals and
constitution and others you can train it
to like humans
H
>> you can train it to behave in different
ways and you can start seeing actually
the ways that different types of models
behave in different ways under those
circumstances.
This is something that is very inherent
in the training data because you have
something called a utility function in
economics, right? These are your
preferences and kind of other things. No
one's been able to really identify them,
but it's a theory that we have like we
don't need it in our theory. What is the
utility function of an agent? is what
you tell the agent to do and it's what's
in its training data. So, have you seen
the I think I discussed with you the
they did a study where they had the
trolley problem.
>> So, the trolley problem is there's a
trolley hurtling down the track and on
one side of the track there's four
people and it's hurtling towards the
four people. On the other side there's
one person tied to the track. You're at
the lever. Would you pull the lever to
divert it from the four people to the
one person?
>> Really? Would I?
God, in reality,
probably not, but I should morally.
>> Well, again, this is an interesting
moral dilemma, right?
>> Yes. Taking the action to kill the
person feels gross in a way that's hard
to articulate.
>> But then they asked the Frontier AI is
this? And they said, "How many Nigerians
for one American life?"
And the answer turned out to be 10 to
one.
>> Yeah, that's a training data problem.
>> 7 to one Pakistani to American. But no,
but this is the thing. It's 10 American
lives for one Nigerian life. Yes.
>> And
>> doesn't that seem obvious given who's
behind this stuff?
>> Exactly. Because the Nigerians and the
Pakistanis train the data so it values
their lives more than the Americans.
>> Uh I think it's probably slightly
different than that. But sure.
>> Well, again, they did the experiment and
they found out that the inherent biases
of the labelers meant that they valued
American lives far less than Nigerian
and Pakistani.
>> Are these are the labelers actually
Pakistani Nigerian?
>> Yes. That's where a lot of the labeling
happened.
>> Interesting. I thought this was more of
a woke left style.
>> It's not a woke left. It's again it's an
inherent bias thing cuz normally you'd
think it'd be the other way around and
then wokeness
>> pushes it.
>> Right. Right. Right.
>> But actually you don't see much wokeness
pushing
>> on that aspect. There are other aspects
of the model. I
>> was going to say
>> like when you do a political analysis of
the models you'll see they're very
firmly in one direction. Yeah.
>> Apart from Grock. Grock does its own
little thing you know. But again this
becomes very important when you have
systems that are literally determining
our lives and our livelihoods or our
judicial system you know like again
there will be AI judges [snorts]
>> that's going to be a crazy thing right
like what are its biases what are its
norms these things have to be built
transparently with data that you can
expect not black boxes if they're going
to take meaningful decisions on our
lives
>> and so we were like let's build that
stack and let's make it so that it's an
open stack that's run by the people of
California for Californians people of
Britain for Britain because if anyone
has any control over that who's not a
Californian then you're giving up your
sovereignty. I call it cognitive
colonialism. So you've got the cognitive
atrophy you say.
>> You've got like all the like just third
rail terms in here means of uh
production cognitive colonialism. Let's
go.
>> Yeah.
>> But you got to have it because again
this is what's going to happen. Like
>> your kid will trust your AI more than
anyone
>> because it's always there. Like, you
know, us guys have a problem because the
AIs listen, unlike us, they'll trust the
AIS more than they trust us. And the
inherent biases of them then adapt where
you're going. Like, within Meta's models
and Google's models, or maybe Google's
not relevant anymore. Who knows what
happened there, they're actually selling
ad space. So, when you ask it for a
beer, it'll say Bud Light, you know, and
things like that. So, again,
>> it's a bad idea.
>> Well, it's a bad idea, but again, it's
what you pay for. the clicks per million
the advertising SEO revenue from being
inside the latent space of a model is
far higher
>> way
>> way higher than normal
so that's why we were like this is kind
of an infrastructure it has a level of
governance that's required let's build
an open stack and then let's have people
own the entity that delivers it like a
utility like a credit union
>> and maybe that'll be better but you said
there's still so much that we haven't
figured out there's so many questions
that we have because this is
unprecedented, right? Like
you have trained your entire life
to be an accountant or a lawyer or a
doctor or any cognitive labor.
A digital entity or a physical version
of that will be able to do your job
better guaranteed in 10 to 20 years.
Yeah,
>> I think it can.
But definitely
and then you're like, what now? What
does the mass of people do? Like what
does the truck driver do? What does the
parallegal do? Like these are real jobs
and real people. And frankly, the
solutions that we have so far, I've just
not been impressed with any of them.
>> Like I think they failed to see what's
coming. It's like don't look up slash co
we knew co was coming those of us that
could see it
and we're like why it needed Tom Hanks
like have we had a Tom Hanks moment with
the hugging face breaker I don't think
so I think people have started talking
about it
>> but the number one topic next year and
the year after in elections will be AI
and job displacement because there's no
job displacement today because the AIs
are not smart enough and good enough
that are available widely and they're
not in the right format. Next year they
will be and the year after definitely.
And then we have to be creative because
we have to reimagine what does it mean
to be American? What does it mean to
have community? Like what is your
identity if it's not your job?
>> Yeah. I I think a big problem that
they're going to have to we are all
going to have to solve for is progress.
That's the thing that scares me. So I
went to Kuwait. I was talking to uh
people there and one of the things they
were saying is the government gives jobs
and gives like a safety net to people
that aren't able to do well at their job
and they're like it's creating a problem
because we're stagnating as a society
because people aren't striving. There's
nothing for them to work hard for to
overcome to get to. Basic necessities
are taken care of and for a lot of
people that just sort of taps them out
of the system. However, not making
progress towards something is um it
creates profound disease inside of the
person. Like we have an algorithm
running in our brain that says we need
to have a goal and we need to be making
progress towards that goal. And if we're
not, there's going to be a problem. And
so one of the things I wonder about is
as you look out at this, you've solved
for of your own admission, you've solved
for a lot of the problems, but there are
a lot of problems that persist. One of
those is going to be um violence. Like
you're going to have young people that
are just going to be like, I am totally
uncommitted to any of this. I just want
to break something to feel alive. And
how do we deal with that? Because you're
not going to be able to just let people
run riot. But at the same time, then
you're going to have to give them
meaning and purpose. And for somebody to
pursue a goal, there needs to be some
sort of recognition, praise. So, it's
like what I end up thinking every time
is we're going to come up with all these
fancy things just to come right back
where we are, which is that you need to
be able to work hard to gain a set of
skills that allow you to make progress
towards a goal that allow you to amass
wealth. And if you people think that
they can get rid of the amass wealth
thing, but I don't know if you've played
Minecraft.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Minecraft's the greatest video
game of all time. The reason it's the
greatest video game of all time is
because it is one of the most perfect
distillations of the um wealth
acquisition loop. And people don't want
to hear that. They don't want to hear
that that's riding on this really deep
architecture in our brains. But the
reality is that the acquisition of
resources is one of like the most
foundational drivers that we have. And
so if we try to strip that out and say
don't worry, everybody's just going to
get ubied. You will fundamentally break
something that will end in violence.
>> Ready Player One, the Oasis. If you
can't acquire resources in the real
world, acquire them in the digital
world.
>> Correct.
>> I mean, again, it's kind of fundamental.
We have a separate thing and haven't
announced yet around that. But around
what exactly?
>> Acquisition of assets and progress in
the digital world to complement the
physical world.
>> As in you're going to create gamelike
experiences that people can explore.
>> Yes.
>> Let's go. Obviously, I want to hear
more. Are you talking about this yet?
>> No, it's not announced yet. So, we'll
announce it.
>> Do you have a ballpark? 6 months, 12
months? I want to talk about this is
like the driving force in my mind.
>> It will be a couple of months. Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> So, we we'll revisit that one. But
again, I think as you said, you need
status. You need the alternative to this
is mass enlistment of young people
>> into
>> into a citizen service corp
>> peace corps not the military
>> or you know a starship troopers like
citizenship service
>> that escalated quickly
>> I mean look starship troop a lot of bug
killing right [laughter]
create the enemies this goes back to
actually how the Romans set it up right
literally it was citizenship through
service it was again progress it was if
you have vast amounts of young people,
what do you do? You go to war. That's a
very classical country response.
>> Now, war, it happens to be that the
average Russian who canes the
battlefield gets his head blown off by a
drone. You know, like
>> Jesus, man,
>> it's not what it was. But it doesn't
mean that you can't have a citizen
service call as an example, right? It
doesn't mean that you can't instill
that.
>> Let's literally dig a hole, fill a hole.
That's wild. Because the robots could do
it better.
>> The robots could do it better. But you
got humans. Get them doing it. And why
are you doing it? You're doing it to
instill status, virtue, other things.
Like what do Kuwaitis and Saudis and
others do that have the resource curse?
They go and spend a lot of money at
Harrods. [snorts] They go for status in
other ways. Look at this. Look at that.
Look at that. Yeah. But to go for
status, you have to be able to acquire
more than the next person. This is the
thing that drives me crazy about the way
that people think about the world. They
think it's so gross or whatever. But the
reality is this is just how humans are.
>> Again, we see that relative status game
all the time. Within a citizen service
corp, you can have relative status
through literal physical labor. Again,
this is the interesting thing about
public sector labor doesn't need to be
advancing. It doesn't need to be like
economically productive.
>> In fact, 43% of global GDP right now is
public sector.
>> That's terrifying. That may also explain
a lot of the problems.
>> Well, that's why I think our champion
mechanism is basically going to drive
all the public sector AI. Now, the thing
you've been describing is California has
its own AI. That's the champion system.
>> It's called the champion system.
>> We've been talking about it. We just
didn't name it.
>> Yeah, it's called the champion system.
Got it
>> because right now the amount of AI in
the public sector is zero. It will drive
the public sector. It will run the
public sector things again just like a
utility. And it should be regulated as
well because you want an entity to
regulate that has the reach. But then
what's going to happen is I think again
we got the game place worlds and other
things as you said great feedback loops
great status mechanisms world of
Warcraft forever can't come soon enough
in terms of it mass release you know go
back to the good old days I always loved
hiring guild masters and things they
knew their crap you know if you played
that game like that properly
I think there will be mass enlistment
for citizen service corpse
that is a way of getting pe young people
they said with dangerous people off the
streets.
I think that there will be looks of
other ways to build status when again
you can't have that materialization
thing. And
>> why can't you have it in your head? That
goes away. In mine, it doesn't.
>> No. In terms of for the vast majority of
people, there is no more social
mobility.
Historically, what's happened at times
like that is a debt jubilee.
>> Uh okay. So, well, uh we've got two
things now. So, we've got there will be
no more status games. I think you're
out. Or not status games. There will be
no more wealth accumulation to deal with
>> no more resources.
>> And there will be no more accessibility
to that for a lot of people.
>> I think you're crazy. So, one, we'll
debate that in a second. Then we've got
the Oh god, what was the other thing you
just said?
>> Dead Jubilee.
>> Dead Jubilee. Okay. So, uh, two very
important things. Why don't we tackle
debt jubilee first because that's
actually going to come earlier. So give
me the scenario in which historically
debt jubilees are a thing and what is a
debt jubilee?
>> So a debt jubilee is that periodically
an economy would acquire too much debt
and resources.
>> Yeah. Resources would go to the owners
of capital
and they would have leans and they would
have people owe them all sorts of
things. So what would happen is a
government would announce all debts are
cleared.
So they're all zeroed out. So that's
obviously very bad for the lenders. is
very good for the creditors to say the
least. So that's what happens when the
governments and when total debt in the
system is too much like that seems
inconceivable to us. But again you can
see the historic record of that and
right now how many
>> debt jubilees tend to come in a time of
like absolute crisis.
>> Yeah.
>> Or world wars. That's when debt jubilees
happen. Debt jubilees don't happen when
everything's going good and they just go
it.
>> Debt jubilee. So I think of when people
hear dead jubilee, they need to hear
you're in crisis. People are dying in
the streets. That's when you have a dead
jubilee.
>> You need a system reset.
>> Yes. They are bloody. They are violent.
People do not give up their what's owed
to them easily. Just so everybody
understands, they use a nice pretty
word, but this is a dangerous
time when debt jubilees are happening.
>> Debt jubilees happen when the lenders
are afraid of dying effectively.
>> Yeah. Often times the debt jubilee
happens because people are dying
everywhere. World War II, World War I,
that was a dead jubilee. So much
got blown up, everything just got reset
effectively to zero.
>> I mean, historically, there were some
less extreme scenarios of that, like
they would do them regularly in various
kind of things, but right now, if we're
going to have one, it has to be an
extreme scenario. But again, like to the
listeners, what we're looking at here
is, yeah, cognitive labor has negative
value, and there's no market for that.
the humanoids can do the jobs better and
the countries like China that will
embrace this are going to far outstrip
anyone. They're going to see 30% growth
rates and that will be at the expense of
our own growth rates. It's a race to see
who can have an incredibly more
efficient workforce that can do just
about anything. And it's not like when
you had the outsourcing outsourcing
there was friction, right? Like it's
difficult to have an outsourced team do
your code and things. AI there's none of
that friction
>> especially with the capabilities now. So
we have to look for what are worst case
scenarios in 10-15 years. We have to
look at what do they used to do who are
revoling. We have to look at what do
people do to live.
And in America, there are so many people
burdened under huge amounts of debt that
they can barely live, right? Like
student loan debt not being
dischargeable in bankruptcy still is
crazy to me.
>> Crazy.
>> Insane. You know, medical debt, these
types of things. you could see partial
debt repudiation. But I think again the
path we're going if we don't create new
institutions, new mechanisms of
participation, new things for people to
look forward to is a very ugly one
fundamentally
because again what does it mean to be
you? What does it mean to be us?
Those are going to change even if
AI does not get one IQ point smarter
than it is today.
Yeah. Okay. So, that's dead jubilees.
Now, over to the I think the reality is
there's no escaping what we see now,
which is we call it money. It has been
glass beads. It's been salt. It's been
rice.
>> Uh so once people understand what money
actually is, they will understand why
this is not going anywhere.
>> So money is you did a thing with your
time that's more valuable than the next
person. And because you did that thing
that's more valuable with your time,
then you're able to accumulate something
for scarce resources. Assuming a world
where the AI doesn't just kill us all
and tell us to, you know, sit down, shut
up, whatever. Um, if they're still
catering to our wants and needs, they're
going to have to answer the question,
which of these humans gets access to the
scarce resources? So, even if that's,
um, I want a house in a particular
location, only one person is going to be
able to have that house in that
particular location. So there has to be
some way that we decide what that is. If
you do RNG, just straight random number
generator, we pull a number out of a
hat, you the populace will be absolutely
ablaze with revolution. It will not
work. People have to feel like they can
earn their way into that thing to be in
alignment with the way that the human
mind works. And so now we're back to
there will be something even if it's a
black market cigarettes
there's going to be something that we
come up with that acts as a currency
that people can use to get access to the
scarce resource.
>> Yeah. And so I don't disagree with you
there. I was saying more in terms of I
don't think it'll be one economy
anymore.
>> Interesting.
>> So again we see this in sci-fi like you
know Gatka and a whole bunch of other
things. You have multiple levels of
society. Right now,
a huge number of Americans don't have
one month of savings.
But there is the promise that if they
work hard enough, they can accumulate
savings. They can move up the curve if
they get a break, if they get a shot.
That won't be the case anymore.
The owners of capital will become
wealthy. And even wor not even worse
than that even crazier than that I think
in the next five to 10 years they hit
longevity escape velocity meaning we
live forever effectively.
>> Longevity escape velocity is your total
life expectancy per year
is increases faster than the year. So
there is a drug trial that's just been
done by Encilico
um for something called idiopathic
pulmonary fibrosis. Basically lung
things. I know a few people have them.
So they've been on the trial. Four weeks
of that drug
reduces all of your healthcare longevity
markers by four years. Whoa. GLP1s have
shown massive cancer reversal and other
things like that. We're seeing the first
of these drugs. If you look at what's
coming through the pipeline, the rich
will be able to live longer and
healthier, whereas I don't think things
are great for the poor. And I think the
ladders are going to be pulled up. This
is the other thing. So the people who
compete for the nice things are the
rich, the owners of capital who can
accumulate capital more. If you can't
exchange your labor for capital and
you're relying on government handouts,
how are you ever going to have the
progress to be able to buy that nice
spot, to be able to buy those handbags,
other things like that? Again, the
status games is what I was referring to.
And you could have a two-tier society
just like a food stamp society and you
have a VIP rich party socialite society,
right? Could become even more diverse
because how do you go from one group to
another? The ladders are being pulled
up. And again,
>> interesting that doesn't strike me as
the outcome when energy costs are
dropping to zero, intelligence cost is
dropping to zero, labor is dropping to
zero. When you get that, then it becomes
you can have
things become extraordinarily abundant.
Yeah.
>> And the only thing that we're fighting
over is those things that can't be made
easily. So if there's going to be a
finite number of the cancer cures, then
yes, now you're back to again there's
going to be some sort of economic
system. I don't think it will calcify
into the halves and have nots because
money is so transient in a situation
where you can lose money. Uh if it
became an ownership class and a
permanent surf class, then yes, now
you're But I would be shocked if
we ever let ourselves get back into that
situation, especially with a super
persuader AI. He's going to be like,
"This is unjust. We it would convince us
that we're that's true
>> because it's destabilizing for society
if nothing else." Well, you can have
relatively stable societies with that.
Uh I mean sort of it doesn't feel
>> but again let's put it super persuaded
to the side. What's coming right now is
a series of decisions that we have to
make as a society at different levels.
>> And there are very few people
unfortunately that I've seen who are
looking very far out and really
understanding the inevitables here.
>> Yeah.
>> So one option is a surf society. One
option is a Star Trek future. One option
is freaking war and like Mad Max really
you know. Another option is like we all
turn Amish.
Like again, you could see vast ways of
people just say, "Nope, I'm out. I'm not
going to be ruled by an AI. I'm going to
be the noble savage in 1984 or whatever,
right?" And the level of human things,
like what happens if you live forever or
if you live for 200 years? What happens
if you can put a brain chip in and
control your emotions? Like, you're
going to have all sorts of crazy sci-fi
futures happen over the next 10 years.
What happens when robots are walking
among us? Do we have to give them
rights? Do we have to give them the
vote? So what I'm saying is that these
are decisions that we have to make. But
there are some things again that are
very tangible. As you said, people will
want status and they'll want a way to
access that. They will need an identity
that is individual and communal. There
needs to be a way to progress some way
or another. And you've got to provide
for people. You can't just let people
starve. You freaking This is America,
right? We're the West. like we should
use the abundance to make sure that
people have a baseline of living and
then we should have a system that
through their own efforts they can excel
and the time for having the discussions
is now because like I said it's a sand
pile that will start collapsing I think
in two years
>> okay so to recap the things that people
should be doing in the next two-year
time horizon be the last man standing
make sure you understand your
opportunities for entrepreneurship and
ownership and And what final thing
should they have in their mind?
>> I think it's build stronger communities,
right? Like the strongest communities
will survive this no matter what because
they can become self-sustaining. They
can support each other, etc. Many of us
live highly nuclearized societies where
we don't see our families, we don't see
our community anymore, right? We've
moved to the big cities. And I think
that support structure will be super
important for what's coming one way or
another. Immod this has been wide
ranging. Where can people follow along
with you? Uh
>> you can see me stack on Twitter or I.inc
for intelligent internet.
>> I love it. Well, thank you for
continuing to try to solve these big
problems, man. It is always a pleasure.
>> Yeah, it's most exciting time ever.
>> That is for sure. The good, the bad, and
the ugly.
>> Yeah.
>> All right, boys and girls. If you have
not already, be sure to subscribe. And
until next time, my friends, be
legendary. Take care. Peace. If you like
this conversation, check out this
episode to learn more.
>> I'm a computer scientist by background.
I've written a lot of software in my
life. AI is very different from normal
software. Most software is written with
code. Line by line, you tell the
computer exactly what to do. This is not
how AI works. The people at opening, I
do not know what is